Guide to the Eastern Wine and Grape Miscellany, 1850-20--, (bulk)1980-20--
Eastern Wine and Grape Miscellany
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Eastern Wine and Grape Miscellany, 1850-20--.
6695
6.5 cubic ft.
Memorabilia, Newspapers, Photographs, Printed Materials, Publications
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Wine and grape industry ephemera, including brochures, newspaper clippings, and other printed material
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Descriptive materials regarding wineries, vineyards, and associated businesses and organizations in the Eastern wine and grape industries. It's geographic scope will include all of the U.S. states east of the Rocky mountains. Currently the majority of the material covers New York State, particularly the Finger Lakes region. Types of materials include but are not limited to: news clippings, magazine articles, brochures, wine trail maps, tasting sheets, price lists and product catalogs.
SUBJECTS
Names:
New York State Agricultural Experiment Station.
Subjects:
Grape industry.; Grape industry--New York (State).; Grapes--New York (State)--Finger Lakes Region.; Viticulture.; Viticulture--New York (State).; Viticulture--New York (State)--Finger Lakes Region.; Wine and wine making.; Wine and wine making--California; Wine and wine making--Canada; Wine and wine making--Illinois; Wine and wine making--Indiana; Wine and wine making--Massachusetts; Wine and wine making--Michigan.; Wine and wine making--New York (State).; Wine and wine making--New York (State)--Finger Lakes Region.; Wine and wine making--Ohio.; Wine and wine making--Pennsylvania.; Wine and wine making--Rhode Island; Wine and wine making--Texas; Wine and wine making--United States.; Wine and wine making--Virginia; Wine and wine making--West Virginia
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Guide lists folders in order as they appear in the boxes.
Items are arranged in specific regions if possible. Documents containing information regarding a broader area over several regions may still contain region and even winery specific information. Undated folders will contain items with bulk dates from 1980s to 2000s. New York State winery items divided by region using in part the Uncork NY website www.newyorkwines.org for winery location information.
NOTES
Forms part of the Eastern Wine and Grape Archive. (EWGA)
SERIES LIST
Series I. Ephemera
Series II. Oversized Ephemera
Series III. Videos
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Ephemera
  - Canandaigua Lake Area winery brochures (Box 1)
  - Canandaigua Lake Area news clippings (Box 1)
  - Keuka Lake winery brochures (Box 1)
  - Keuka Lake news clippings (Box 1)
  - West side Seneca Lake winery brochures (Box 1)
  - West side Seneca Lake news clippings (Box 1)
  - East side Seneca Lake winery brochures (Box 1)
  - East side Seneca Lake news clippings (Box 1)
  - Cayuga Lake winery brochures (Box 1)
  - Cayuga Lake news clippings (Box 1)
  - Canandaigua Lake wine trail brochures (Box 1)
  - Keuka Lake wine trail brochures (Box 1)
  - Seneca Lake wine trail brochures (Box 1)
  - Cayuga Lake wine trail brochures (Box 1)
  - Hudson Cattell, Covering the Eastern Wine Beat talk at the NYS Agricultural Experiment Station. Also see the videos of this event., April 2007 (Box 2)
  - The First New York State Fair Wine Awards Tasting Competition, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Concord Grape Belt Heritage Association, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Lake Erie Regional Grape Program and New York State Integrated Pest Management Program, 2005 (Box 2)
  - Non-wine related industry brochures of places on NY wine trails (Box 2)
    Includes Bed and Breakfasts, museums, the Rose Inn.
  - New York State winery advertisement clippings, 1940s-1950s (Box 2)
  - New York State wine ephemera, 1960s-1980s (Box 2)
  - New York State Supreme Court direct shipping decision news clippings, 2005 (Box 2)
  - New York Wine and Culinary Center Canandaigua news clippings, includes tasting sheets from events, 2005 (Box 2)
  - Constellation Brands - news clippings including takeover of Vincor International Inc.., 2005- (Box 2)
  - New York State - Chautauqua and Lake Erie area ephemera, ca 2000s (Box 2)
    Includes parts of Ohio, Pennsylvania. Includes early 1900s Chautauqua Grape Belt postcards, history of the grape belt items..
  - Double A Vineyards Inc. (Box 2)
  - New York State- Niagara and Lake Ontario area ephemera (Box 2)
  - Vizcarra Vineyards at Becker Farms (Box 2)
  - Warm Lake Estate (Box 2)
    Also includes information about Niagara escarpment region and wine trail.
  - New York State- Hudson Valley area ephemera (Box 2)
    In particular Millbrook and North Salem Wineries.
  - New York State- Long Island area ephemera (Box 2)
  - New York State- Upstate and Thousand Islands ephemera (Box 2)
  - New York State associated wine industry ephemera. Includes CD-ROM presentation of a feasibility study for Cornell University Wine Stewards, done for a class. (Box 2)
    Includes wine tours and wine stores
  - New York winery, vineyard, and fruit tree surveys (Box 2)
  - Early clippings and ephemera, 1850-1900 (Box 3)
    Includes Pleasant Valley, Gold Seal, Montage, Urbana, Seneca Chief, Vivard & Sheehan, Lake Keuka Wine Company, Hammondsport Vintage Company. November 1890 article from American Garden about wine making and grape growing by Bauder of PV.
  - List of bonded wineries and their dates., ca. 1934 (Box 3)
  - Taylor, Bully Hill, Great Westerm Gold Seal (Charles Fournier), Urbana ephemera. Includes Vineyard to Fermenter paper by Domenic A. Carisetti, Taylor winemaker., 1970s (Box 3)
  - The Taylor Wine Company, Inc. Annual Reports, bound together, 1960-1976 (Box 3)
    Seaton C. Mendall former owner.
  - Conversation with Jimmy Frisk & Mike Brace of Taylor Wine Company, July 22, 1980 (Box 3)
    Audio cassette originally recorded by Walter S. Taylor of Bully Hill. Frisk and Brace were employees of the Taylor Wine Company. Includes discussion of Greyton H. Taylor, Fred Taylor, Clarence Taylor, what Frisk and Brace were paid, ancedotes, and a party at which there will be the naming of a goat, perhaps the Bully Hill goat.
  - Files, brochures, and correspondence relating to the origins of Cornell's Eastern Wine and Grape Archive, early collecting, and wine history references., 1996-2007 (Box 3)
    Includes info on the Philip Wagner collection, American Society for Enology and Viticulture involvement, lists of sources / books of wine history useful for the collection. Correspondence include Bruce Reisch, Justin Morris, and others. This info is available as digital files on CD-975 in folder. Also included is a copy of the paper "Wine Making In Canada and the Eastern United States" by Jacklin, Sharron, and Fordon, See also call number SB387.2 I575 2007 for other material relating to the conference where this paper was presented..
  - Mike Fordon files regarding Taylor and Pleasant Valley Wine Company movies and their conservation, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Swedish Hill Winery new employee packet, ca. 1995 (Box 3)
  - Boordy Vineyards, Philip Wagner, ca. 1960-1971 (Box 3)
  - Cornell University wine related ephemera and clippings, ca. 2000s (Box 3)
  - Geneva / Cornell University "Grape Crusher" clippings, ca. 2000s (Box 3)
  - New York State Agricultural Experiment Station Geneva ephemera (Box 3)
    Includes lables by George Remaily for Geneva Cellars
  - New York State Agricultural Experiment Station and New York Wine and Grape Foundation research grants (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Tending the Vineyards: Renewed Growth for New York's Grape/Wine Industry, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Uncork New York press kit and brochures, 1970s-2000s (Box 3)
    Includes Guide to 1977-1978 New York wines
  - National - wine and grape industry retailers, 1950s-2000s (Box 3)
    Includes 19907 brochure for U.S. Bottlers' Supply Company
  - National - wine and grape industry information, cookbooks, wine making. Cork brochure; Year in the life of a winemaker pamphlet; How to read a wine label brochure; etc.., 1950s-2000s (Box 3)
  - Material from Viticulture 2007 tradeshow in Rochester (Box 3)
  - Dreams Into Nectar Volume I. Collision Course: Wine and Temperance, 2012 (Box 3)
    Finger Lakes Museum exhibition show on wine history
  - eSkye (Box 5)
  - Wine and grape associations (Box 5)
  - Grape and grower specific ephemera, includes prices, vineyard costs, 1970s-2000s (Box 5)
  - National Grape Cooperative Association, Inc. and Welch Foods Inc. (Box 5)
  - Wine bottle tags (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous United States and International winery brochures and ephemera: Alabama, Chile, Japan, Kentucky, Maryland, Minnesota, Missouri, New Jersey, Oregon, Texas. (Box 5)
  - California ephemera, includes 1975-1978 calendars showing wineries (Box 5)
  - Indiana and Illinois ephemera (Box 5)
  - New England, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, Vermont ephemera (Box 5)
  - Michigan, Minnesota ephemera, includes La Salle Wines and Champagne, Inc. stock certificate. (Box 5)
  - Florida, Maryland, North Carolina and South Carolina ephemera (Box 5)
  - Ohio ephemera (Box 5)
  - Pennsylvania ephemera (Box 5)
  - Pennsylvania Association of Wine Growers and Penn State Extension (Box 5)
  - Virginia and West Virginia ephemera (Box 5)
  - Canada Ontario Niagara on the Lake region wineries (Box 5)
  - Canada Ontario Niagara on the Lake region trails, societies, associated industry ephemera (two folders) (Box 5)
  - New York Wine Course and Reference Binder., 1989 (Box 6)
    Current course packet can be found online here.
  - National - wine and grape news clippings, 1950s (Box 6)
  - National - wine and grape news clippings, 1960s (Box 6)
  - National - wine and grape news clippings, 1970s (Box 6)
  - National - wine and grape news clippings, 1980s- (Box 6)
  - New York State general news clippings (Box 6)
    Some info on the 1986 grape crash.
  - New York State wine selling in grocery store clippings (Box 6)
  - Finger Lakes area wine and grape industry news clippings (two folders + many loose publications) (Box 6)
  - Finger Lakes general area tourism and wine trail brochures and maps, wine guild (two folders) (Box 6)
  - New York State wine event ephemera (two folders) (Box 8)
    Includes Cayuga Wine Trail Wine and Herb Fest
    Seneca Lake Winery Whale Watch event
    New York Heritage Collection unveiling, with wine labels
  - European Wine Ephemera (two folders) (Box 8)
  - Document Heritage Preservation Project
    - Wineries and vineyards schedules and lists, 2004-2005 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - EWGA letters/drafts, 2004-2005 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - EWGA project notes, 2005-2006 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Cayuga Lake Wine Trail, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Seneca Lake Wine Trail, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Keuka Lake Wine Trail, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Finger Lakes Wine Guild, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Cattell- Encyclopedia Art. Wines (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Curtiss Museum, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Oliver House survey Penn Yan, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - T. Martinson Talk, Oliver House, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Taylor Museum- P. Sprague, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Series II. Oversized Ephemera
  - Posters: Finger Lakes Fall Festival October 1979; Wickham Vineyards (Hector, NY); Dr Konstantin Frank's vineyards, 1970s-1980s (Box 4)
  - "Uncork New York" Wine Advertising posters from the New York Wine and Grape Foundation. Includes maps of the principal New York State Wine Districts, a poster listing New York State Gold Wines and Vineyards, and treatments of the sherry "Uncork New York" logo and its application to letterheads by Ketchum Public Relations, 1987, 1980s-2000s (Box 4)
  - Advertising proofs for New York wines, ca. 1986 (Box 4)
  - Wine catalog for Sherry Wine & Spirits Co. Inc. Includes prices and descriptions of wine and liquor. Also includes listings for some vintages for sale dating back to 1818. Illustrated with drawings by Pablo Picasso with article about him by Alfred Frankfurter., ca. 1960 (Box 4)
  - Large photo of the George Remaily Seedless grape; Posters of Delaware, Niagare, Cataruba and isabella grapes. Large pictures of the Graaf Reinet Museum and its exhibit of the "Largest Living Grape Vine in the World" (Box 4)
  - Star Gazette articles on the New York wine industry, January 5, 2003 (Box 4)
  - 4 Calendars: California Wineries, 1975-1978 (Box 4)
- Series III. Videos
  - Savor the flavor, romancing America's grape. Lake Erie Concord grape belt, produced by the Concord Grape Belt Heritage Association., 2006; DVD #47
    This item is in collection #6718, listed here for cross reference.
  - Wine Country ... USA produced by Taylor Wine Co., 1964; DVD #56 (Box 7)
    DVD copied from original film reel.
  - Wine is to Enjoy produced by Great Western Wines, 1969; DVD #57 (Box 7)
  - One Hundred Vintage Years produced by Gold Seal Vineyards, 1969; DVD #58 (Box 7)
  - Hudson Cattell, Covering the Eastern Wine Beat talk at the NYS Agricultural Experiment Station., April 17, 2007; DVD #96 (Box 7)
  - Wines by Taylor. Presented by the Taylor Wine Company Hammondsport, NY. Conceived and directed by Greyton H. Taylor, Fred C. Taylor, and Clarence W, Taylor., ca. March 1938; DVD #169 (Box 7)
    DVD copied from original film reel. VHS copy available in collection #6718, V-732. Also on Betacam tape V-733.
  - The Story of Wine: The Pleasant Valley Wine Company. Produced by Richard M. Moore, Rochester Cinema Lab., ca. 1940; DVD #170 (Box 7)
    DVD copied from original film reel also on Betacam tape V-734.
  - The U.S. - Canada Free Trade Agreement: An Emerging Market for New York Wines. Student video project for class in export marketing, made with Uris Media facilities. (VHS), December 1, 1988; V-841 (Box 7)
  - Hudson Cattell, Covering the Eastern Wine Beat talk at the NYS Agricultural Experiment Station. (VHS), April 17, 2007; V-842 (Box 7)
  - A history of wine in America ‡b from the beginnings to prohibition., June 5, 2008; DVD #1183 (Box 7)
    Thomas Pinney's lecture in association with the exhibition Song of the Vine and Pinney's book.
  - Independent Stave Company ASEV 95, V-10703 (Box 7)
  - "A Lesson in Home Wine Making", V-10704 (Box 7)
    Production of Ohio State University
  - The Grapevine cassette, September 23, 2001; tr-17133 (Box 7)